The Doctor, together with his friends Ben, Polly and Jamie,
博士，和他的朋友 Ben, Polly 和 Jamie 一起
defeated the insane professor Zaroff to blow up the world.
挫败了疯狂教授 Zaroff 要炸毁全世界的计划
Leaving Atlantis behind, the Doctor set course for Mars
离开了亚特兰蒂斯，博士设定了去往火星的航向
But then the TARDIS goes wildly out of control.
但 TARDIS 开始完全失控了...
Anyone would think we got rats up here.
谁会想到这里还会有老鼠
WHO IS THAT?!
谁在那儿？
Who is it?
是谁？
Moonbase
月球基地
Doctor, do something!
博士，做点什么啊！
I'm trying to!
我正努力呢
Everything back under control again.
一切又恢复掌控控之中了
Here, we're landing! Look!
我们快着陆了，看！
Oh, thank the lord for that. You know, Doctor,
I'll never ask you to do that again.
噢，感谢上天。博士，我再也不让你那么做了
There must be a reason for that.
出现这个情况肯定是有原因的
Hey, wait a mo! This doesn't look like Mars to me.
嘿，等一下！我觉得这里不像是火星
How do you know? You never seen it.
你怎么知道？你又从来没见过
No, Duchess, but I have seen pictures of the moon surface
and that's what this looks like.
是没见过，夫人。但我看过月球表面的照片，这跟那个很像啊
That's the moon?
那是月球？
Doctor, is it the moon?
博士，这是月球吗？
Oh well, you weren't too far out, were you?
Only two hundred million miles!
那个，你没有偏离多远吧，对不？不到两亿英里！
All right, let's move on - while we can.
好啦，我们继续前进吧 - 趁着还能
- What!
- Now wait a minute! You don't expect to land us
on the moon and let us fly off just like that, do you?
- 什么！ - 等一下！你不会指望把我们拉到月球, 然后就马上把我们拉走吧，是吧？
Yeah, at least let us have a look around!
是啊，至少我们得四周转转
That picture canna be the moon? The moon's way up in the sky.
那个镜头不可能是月球。月球正在天上呢
Where do you think you're going?
你觉得你要去哪儿？
You're not going to tell us there is no shore leave?
你不会告诉我们没有上岸假期吧？
Oh please Doctor. The TARDIS isn't out of control or anything is it?
噢求你了，博士。TARDIS没有失控什么的吧？
Oh no, no, no. Just a bumpy landing. That's all
没没没，只是着陆有点颠簸，仅此而已
Yeah?
嘢？
Well, if you must go ashore... only half an hour.
好吧，如果你们要上岸...只有半个小时
- Right.
- Superb
- 好  - 太棒了
You can't go ashore like that!
You need space suits, there's no atmosphere out there.
你们不能就这样上岸啊！你们需要太空服，外面没有空气
Come on, there's some in the chest.
来，箱子里有几件
Maybe we'll meet the old man in the moon.
也许我们能碰到月球上最老的人
You won't meet anybody mate if you don't get some gear on.
如果你不穿上一些装备, 你就碰不到任何人了
What? Oh aye.
什么？是啊
Hey, look at this.
嘿，看看这个
Its deserted.
这里很荒凉
Yeah, I don't think I like it.
是啊，我觉得我不喜欢它
Hey, what do we need this great clogs for?
嘿，我们需要这个大木块做什么？
Try a little jump.
试着轻轻跳一下
All right.
好啊
Careful! One tear in that space suit and you'll suffocate.
小心点！太空服破一个口子你们就会窒息
Come on, it's easy.
来吧，很容易的
Look out, here I come.
小心，我来了
Where's he gone?
他去哪儿了？
Over there.
在那边
What on Earth? Look!
这是什么？看！
Blimey! What is it?
啊呀，那是什么？
Doctor, what is it?
博士，它是什么？
I don't know.
我不知道
Hey, I can see Jamie, there he is.
嘿，我看见 Jamie 了，他在那儿
Hey, there's somebody coming out.
嘿，有人出来了
Come on, let's go.
快来，我们走
And... Jules, you take over.
然后... Jules，你接手
There must be some source to this infection. /
这种感染一定有某种来源。
Look, then get the lads in here and tell them what's happening. /
听着, 就把小伙子们都叫进来, 告诉他们发生了什么事。
Get them on the blower would you, Nils.
让他们在鼓风机上, 可以吗，Nils？
Hello. Where did you lot spring from? /
你好，你们是从哪里蹦出来的？
Don't tell me the shuttle rocket arrived already?
别告诉我穿梭火箭已经到了？
No, it hasn't.
不，它没有
There was another one with them, sir.
Bob taken him along to the Medical unit.
他们还有一个人，头儿．Bob 已经将他带到医务室去了
He's all right. He's just knocked himself out or something.
他没大碍，只是自己撞到什么东西上了
Oh no, if we haven't got enough troubles already.
噢不，好像我们麻烦还不够多似的
We don't want to cause you any trouble.
Just let us collect our young friend and we'll be off.
我们不会给你们添麻烦的。让我们去接我们的年轻朋友, 然后我们就离开
Hey, not so fast.
嘿，别这么着急
Please let me go and see Jamie.
请让我走，我要去看看 Jamie
I will take you there Mademoiselle. If you come with me.
我带你去那里，小姐，请跟我来
All right, young lady. You can carry on.
好吧，年轻女士，你可以去
This way.
这边
Well, you know what this place is?
对了，你知道这是什么地方吗？
Well, it looks like some sort of weather control centre.
这个嘛，看起来像是某种天气控制中心
Ah, yes. And that's the thing with which
you control the weather. That's the culprit then.
啊，是的。那就是用来控制天气的东西。它那就是罪魁祸首了
Hey?
嗯？
Hmmm. That's what gave us a bumpy landing.
嗯，就是那东西让我们着陆时颠簸
- Hm-Hmm.
- I see
- 嗯哼  - 我明白了
The gravitron controls the tides, the tides controls the weather.
引力创控制潮汐，潮汐就控制天气
And from this console we can plot it all on that map.
然后从这个控制台，我们可以将这一切绘制在那个地图上
Simple, eh?
简单不？
Yeah, very simple.
是，非常简单
It's Jim. Quick Francois, take over.
是 Jim。快点，Francois，你接手
International Space Control Earth calling
Weather Control Moon - come in please.
国际空间控制中心地球站呼唤天气控制中心月球站 - 听到请回答
Moonport - standing by.
月球基地 正在待命
Ever seen anything like that before, Doctor?
以前见过这样的情况吗，博士？
Hobson here.
我是 Hobson
What's happening up there? The hurricane you were guiding
is now 45 degrees off course. It's threatening Hawaii.
上面发生什么事了？你所引导的飓风现在偏离了45度。它正在威胁夏威夷
One of my men were taken ill. We're operational again now.
我的一个手下生病了。我们已恢复运作
The controller would like to know the cause of the illness.
控制方想知道疾病的原因
Yes, so would we. We now have three men down /
with this mysterious virus in the past few hours - including the Doctor.
是，我们也想知道。在过去的几个小时里, 我们现在已经有三个人
因为这种神秘的病毒倒下了 -- 包括医生本人
One moment please. Stand by for further instructions.
稍等一下，请等候进一步通知
Just hang on for another couple of minutes lads.
We better hear what the great Mr. Rinberg has to say.
再等几分钟, 小伙子们．我们最好听听伟大的林伯格先生有什么话要说
We're being monitored again.
我们又被监听了
Monitored?
监听？
Someone, not too far away from the base,
is listening to every word we say.
某个人，正在离基地不远的地方，监听着我们说的每一个字
"Moonbase, Moonbase, come in Moonbase. "
月球基地，月球基地，收到请回话
Still standing by.
If you radio information about this virus,
we can do our best to identify it and suggest treatment.
如果你将这种病毒的信息传送过来, 我们可以尽最大努力识别它, 并给出治疗建议
I demand to speak to Rinberg.
我请求与Rinberg通话
The controller is busy - I'm sorry. Over and out.
控制员正忙，对不起。结束通话
That whole conversion was monitored by someone or something.
整个通话过程都被监听了，被某个人或某种东西
Oh, never mind about that now.
That Rinberg fellow won't talk to you.
哦, 现在别管那个了。Rinberg 那个家伙不会和你说话的
How can we trace down this mystery illness
with the Doctor himself down with it.
我们怎样才能追查出这种神秘的疾病的来源呢，我们的医生都被他干倒了
We better get out of these things and see how Jamie is.
Perhaps I can be of help in the sick bay now.
我们最好先出身去看看 Jamie 怎么样了。也许现在我可以在医务室帮上点忙
Anything you can do... Bob!
能做些什么就做吧...Bob！
Yes, Mr Hobson?
什么，Hobson 先生？
Show them to the Medical unit will you?
带他们去医务室，可以吗？
Yes, of course. Now, if you will come this way, please?
好的，当然。现在，你们来这边吧，请
Yes. Thank you.
好。谢谢你
Well, you all heard the position. We don't know
what this infection is and how it got into the base
好了，当前的情况你们都听到了。我们不知道这种传染病是什么，是怎么进到基地的
but I want you all to take extra precautions
while this emergency is on
但当前还是紧急状态，我期望你们都千万小心
We may be short-handed for quite a while.
我们在相当一段时间内可能会人手不足
Is this how its goes, Doctor?
它就是这样运作的吗，博士？
Yes, that's right. Then, this unit automatically
controls the pulse, the temperature and the breathing.
对，就是那样。然后，这个设备会自动控制脉搏、体温和呼吸
A sort of electronic Doctor.
像是个电子医生
Yes.
对
And it even give you medicines too?
而且它还能给配药吗？
Yes. It will do very nearly everything.
是的，它差不多能干所有事了
How do you think he is, Doctor?
你觉得他状态怎么样，博士？
Oh, he's not too bad. He's a bit concussed
and feverish but he'll be all right with rest.
哦，并不差。他有点脑震荡和发烧，但休息一下就没事了
The Piper! The McCrimmon Piper! Don't let him get me!
风笛手！McCrimmon家的风笛手！别让他抓走我！
Piper?
风笛手？
Some legend of his clan. As far, as I can make out
- this piper appears to a McCrimmon just before he dies.
他们家族的某个传说。据我推测，McCrimmon 家族的人死之前这个风笛手就会出现
Has this phantom piper appeared to Jamie yet?
那这个幽灵风笛手在 Jaime 面前出现了吗？
You don't believe it, do you?
你不会相信这个吧，会吗？
No, but he does. It's important to him.
不信，但他信，这对他很重要
He keeps asking us to keep the piper away from him.
他不停地要求我们不让那个风笛手靠近他
Good. We can see if we can do just that.
好，我们看看能不能做到
Well, carry on Nurse.
好了，继续吧护士
Well, at least I try to help. There's a ward full of sick men
and no doctor. Somebody got to do something.
嗯，至少我会尽量帮忙。这里满是病人，没有医生，得有人做点什么
I wonder who this is?
咦，这是谁？
Don't get too near. Have a look on his chart.
别太近了，看看他的记录
That's a good idea.
这是个好注意
It's Dr. Evans.
是 Evans 医生
Oh, yes. The station doctor. He was the first one to get it.
哦，对，站内的医生。他是第一个得病的
He looks one of the worst.
他是看起来情况最严重的
There's something about this epidemic
that I... I just don't understand.
对于这个流行病，有一些是我...不能理解的
It's not like a real disease at all! It's almost like...
看着就不像一种真正的疾病，完全像是...
Not real! What more do you want?
不是真正的！你还想要多真？
I don't know. But there are certain signs and symptoms
which don't add up.
我不知道，但这里有一些体征和症状相互矛盾
Ben, I want you to go to the control room and keep an eye on things.
Ben，我要你到控制室去，盯着点
But how?
怎么盯？
Give a hand, do anything but keep your eyes and ears open.
帮帮忙什么的，做什么都行，不过眼睛要放亮点
Right.
好
There's something very wrong here. Something very wrong indeed.
这里有些事情非常不对劲，真的非常不对劲
Still up, Nobby. Why not take a rest. Go and get some sleep.
还没睡啊, Nobby, 为什么不休息一下, 去睡一下吧
Oh, How can I rest with that thing up the spout.
You know the score as well as I do.
噢, 有了这事儿我这么还能睡得着啊, 你跟我一样清楚现在的状态
Five units off centre and we lift half London into space!
偏离中心五个单位, 半个伦敦就被抬到空中了
Five more and the Atlantic water level goes up three feet!
再偏五个单位, 大西洋的水平面就得上升三尺！
Rinberg don't understand the pressure we're under.
Rinerg 并不理解我们当前的压力
Hey you! What do you thinking you are doing?! Skulking here?
嘿你！你在干什么呢！在这里躲懒吗?
Just wondering if I can help, sir.
只是看看有什么能帮上忙的, 先生
Well, how can you help?
哦, 你能帮什么忙？
We can do with an extra pair of hands - he can help me.
我们这边需要多几个人手 - 他可以来帮我
Well, keep him away from me, that's all.
行, 别让他在我这里晃悠就行了．
All right, I'll go and lie down. Call me if anything happens.
好了, 我走了, 去躺躺．如果有任何事就叫我
Yes, of course.
好的, 没问题
Oh, by the way, there were two more of those momentary drops
in air pressure while I was on.
哦, 顺便说一下, 我在这里的时候又出现过两次短暂的气压下降
I have put them in the log.
我都记在日志里面了
Right.
好的
What is that?
那是什么？
Shhhh, it's all right Polly. It's only me.
We don't want to wake everybody up do we?
嘘, 没事的 Polly．就我一个．我们不想吵醒每一个人吧
You look if you can do with some sleep yourself.
你看起来也需要睡一会儿
I'm all right.
我没事
What have you got there?
你那边发现什么了吗？
Oh, I been doing a little investigation.
哦, 我做了一点调查
A piece of silver paper. What is it?
一小块银箔, 是什么东西？
I don't know.
我不知道
What's happened?!
什么情况？
Oh, it's nothing. It probably just a changeover in the time cycle.
哦, 没事．只是人工昼夜交替而已
What do you mean?
什么意思？
Oh, you see - it's rather interesting really
哦, 你看, 这真的很有意思
you see on the moon, they have a fortnight of days
and a fortnight of nights.
你看看月球, 他们有长达１４天的白天和１４天的黑夜
Well?
是吗？
Well, it's oblivious isn't it? They have to
make their own day and night artificially up there
是啊, 这很明显啊是不？他们这里就不得不靠人工制造白天和黑夜
Or it would upset their own biological time clock.
否则他们的生物钟就会紊乱
Their what?
他们的什么？
They won't know if they were coming or going. Get it?
他们就不知道该起床还是睡觉了, 明白了吗？
Yes.
哦
Clever girl. QED. That's why it's dark up here.
聪明. 证明完毕．这就是为什么现在这里黑了
Oh, I see what you mean. Yes, of course. How stupid of me.
哦, 我明白你什么意思了．对了, 当然．我真是太蠢了
Of course along the control centre it's probably broad daylight.
当然了在控制中心那边可能一直都是白天
Polly, you wouldn't be making fun of me would you?
Polly, 你不是在逗我吧, 是吗？
No.
不！
Dr. Evans.
Evans 医生
The hand. No, don't touch me. No. The silver hand.
手, 不, 不要碰我．不, 银色的手
Doctor, is he...
博士, 他是不是．．．
Yes, I'm afraid he is.
是的, 恐怕他是
What are we gone to do?
那我们该做什么？
What does he means by the silver hand.
I better report this to Mr. Hobson.
他说＂银色的手＂是什么意思？我最好向 Hobson 先生报告一下
What's the matter?
什么情况？
Something just went out of that door!
什么东西从那个门跑出去了！
Nils! John!
What was it?
是什么东西？
Nothing. Nothing there.
没有, 那里什么也没有
Your nerves are getting the better of you. Where's Evan's body?
你太神经过敏了．Evan 的尸体呢？
Over there.
在那边
All right, let's get it over with.
好了, 让我们结束吧
Is this somebody's idea of a particularly bad joke?
这是谁开的恶意玩笑吗？
This is no joke, believe me!
这不是玩笑, 相信我！
Mr. Hobson, Mr. Hobson, you are wanted!
Hobson 先生, Hobson 先生, 这里需要你
Another man's collapsed at the controls
and the Gravitron has been thrown off alignment again.
控制室又有一个人倒下了, 引力创也又一次跑偏了
Come on!
快来！
And you better find that Doctor's body or out you all go
- quarantine or no quarantine.
你们最好找到医生的尸体, 否则你们都得出去 - 不管隔离不隔离
I don't understand what could have happened.
I must have dozed off or something
我不清楚刚才可能发生了什么, 我肯定是打盹了
but one thing I am sure of
- something went out of that door just as you came in.
但有一件事我可以肯定：你进来的时候有什么东西跑出那个门去了
That body can't just have vanished.
Polly, I am going to leave you alone...
尸体不可能凭空消失的．Polly, 我得让你一个人在这里...
...just for a minute.
...就几分钟
All right.
好的
Water. Water.
水．水
I'll go and get you some.
我去给你弄点
Water!
水！
It's you! The phantom piper!
是你！幽灵风笛手！